A Finding Aid to the Doug Edge papers, circa 1951-2017, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Doug Edge papers
circa 1951-2020
Archives of American Art
Edge, Doug, 1942-
AAA.edgedoug
Archival Resource Key
2.9 Linear feet
The papers of Los Angeles conceptual sculptor, painter, and photographer Doug Edge measure 2.9 linear feet and date from circa 1951 to 2017. The collection includes exhibition and project files, illustrated journals, writings, printed material, photographic material, and artwork. There is a 0.2 linear foot unprocessed addition to this collection donated in 2021 that includes a self published book and notes, dating from 1969-2020.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in seven series.
Series 1: Exhibition and Project Files, circa 1951-2017 (Box 1; 1 linear foot, ER01; 10 files, 4.36 GB)
Series 2: Illustrated Journals, 1968-2010 (Box 2; 1 linear foot)
Series 3: Writings, 1974, 2017 (Box 3; 2 folders)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1963-1997, 2009-2016 (Boxes 3-4; 0.3 linear feet, OV 5)
Series 5: Photographic Material, 1962-1987, 2003-2017 (Box 4; 2 folders, OV 5, ER02; 138 files, 0.44 GB)
Series 6: Artwork, 1962-1984, 2002, 2007 (Box 4; 1 folder, OV 5)
Series 7: Unprocessed Addition, 1969-2020 (Box 6; 0.2 linear feet)
Biographical / Historical
Doug Edge (1942- ) is a conceptual sculptor, painter, and photographer in Los Angeles, California. Edge was a member of the acrylic movement in the late 1960s. He was an original faculty member at the California Institute of the Arts (Cal Arts) from 1969 to 1971, and taught at the University of California, Santa Barbara from 1974 to 1985.
Edge began showing his work in the late 1960s and continues to produce and exhibit work. He has shown at Mizuno, Cirrus, Earl McGrath, and Track 16 Galleries, among many others.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center. Use of electronic records with no duplicate access copies requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Doug Edge in 2017 and 2021.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Los Angeles conceptual sculptor, painter, and photographer Doug Edge measure 2.9 linear feet and date from circa 1951 to 2020. The collection includes exhibition and project files, illustrated journals, writings, printed material, photographic material, and artwork. There is a 0.2 linear foot unprocessed addition to this collection donated in 2021 that includes a self published book and notes. Materials date from 1969-2020.
Exhibition and project files include correspondence, photographs, slides, transparencies, sketches, writing, clippings, and other printed material related to Edge's exhibitions, projects, and work. This series also includes some biographical material and material related to his student work. Also included in this series are digital videos related to Edge's artwork and exhibitions.
Illustrated journals contain drawings, sketches, writings, plans for work and exhibitions, photographs, etc. Some in the series are primarily image-based, while others have more text.
Writings include a statement written by Doug Edge in 2017 and a transcript, in scroll format, of a lecture by Robert Irwin at the University of California, Santa Barbara in 1974.
Printed material includes exhibition announcements; exhibition catalogs; the magazines Eclipse and Forum; clippings; posters; and a copy of James Turrell's syllabus and course materials for a course taught at the University of California, Santa Barbara.
Photographic material includes photographs Edge took on a trip with James Turrell to Monument Valley and Lake Powell; photographs and digital photographs of works of art; and oversized photographs related to his exhibitions.
Artwork includes sketches, drawings, watercolors, silk screen prints, paintings, and other works of art.
Art -- Study and teaching; Conceptual artists -- California; Painters -- California -- Los Angeles; Photographers -- California -- Los Angeles; Sculptors -- California -- Los Angeles; Monument Valley (Ariz. and Utah); Powell, Lake (Utah and Ariz.); Diaries; Drawings; Video recordings; Irwin, Robert, 1928-; Turrell, James
- Exhibition and Project Files, circa 1951-2017; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1; 4.36 Gigabytes 10 computer files
  Scope and Contents
  Exhibition and project files include correspondence, photographs, slides, transparencies, sketches, writing, clippings, and other printed material related to Edge's exhibitions, projects, and work. This series also includes some biographical material, material related to his student work, his time as an instructor at the University of California, Santa Barbara (UCSB), and artist statemetns and other writings. Also included in this series is are digital videos related to Edge's artwork and exhibitions.
  Arrangement
  The documents in this series were originally housed in eight binders with tabs for each identified project or exhibition in rough-chronological ordger. During processing these tabs were separated into individual folders with the headings and order retained. The first folder includes a list, compiled by Doug Edge, with the contents and order of the original eight "books" (i.e. binders). The born-digital records have been added to the end of this series.
  - Introduction and Student Work, circa 1951; 1962-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gallery Shows: Gallery 66, Gallery 669, Mizuno Gallery, 1963-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Resin Bag Castings, 1969-1973; 2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Market Street Program and Cirrus Gallery, 1971, 1970-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Move to Amsterdam, 1972-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Malibu Mountains, Tuna Canyon, Venice Studio, 1971-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Santa Barbara, Foldout Staircase Show at Cirrus Gallery, Global Kiva Tableau Show at Santa Barbara Museum, Isometric Staircase Show at Cirrus Gallery, 1975-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Edge Totums, Swope Gallery Show, Gregory Ghent Gallery Show, UCSB College of Creative Studies Show, Space Gallery Show, 1981-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ladder Figures, Traveling Museum Show Adjustments Must Be Made Continually, Earl McGrath Show, Essays and Reviews, circa 1983-circa 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chip Carved Wall Hangings, circa 1987-1991; 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Teaching at UCSB and Art Center, Curved Space, 1976-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Abstract Paintings, 1976-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Constructivist Pagota, 1974-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Earl McGrath Show The Water Planet, Earl McGrath Insect Show, Insect Paintings, The Pest Equation, 1988-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Black Hole Work, Works Gallery Show, 1989-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tri Gallery Show, Therapy Work, 1990-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 4D Corn Pieces, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Thorn Pieces, Digital Prints, 1996-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gracie Mansion Show, N.Y.; Grovesnor Gallery Show, London, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Road Sign Paintings, 2001-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Container Ship Paintings, Container Paintings, 2002-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 2008 Sculpture in New Studio, 2006-circa 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Track 16 Show, 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 2006-2008 Paintings, 1997; 2007-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Slam Paintings, 2009-2010; 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cardwell Jimmerson Show, David Richard Show, 2010; 2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Launch Gallery Show, Christine Nichols Project Show, 2013; 2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Smithsonian Archive, 2015-2017 Paintings and Sculpture, 2015-circa 2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Art Statements, 1979; 1989-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, Journals, Lists, 1970-1977; 1987-1999; 2010-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Digital Videos, 2014-2017; Archival Resource Key; 4.36 Gigabytes 10 computer files (Box ER01)
- Illustrated Journals, 1968-2010; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 2
  This series includes 14 notebooks containing drawings, sketches, plans for work and exhibitions, photographs, writings, etc. Some journals function primarily as sketchbooks and have little to no text, while others include more writing.
  - Illustrated Journal, 1968-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Illustrated Journal, 1972 August-1973 December; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Aloha Personal Symbolism", 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Trip with James Turrell to See his Volcano", 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Illustrated Journals, 1983 August-2006 December; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5-13)
  - Untitled Journal, 2007-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Writings, 1974; 2017; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 3
  Writings include a statement written by Doug Edge in 2017 and a transcript, in scroll format, of a lecture by Robert Irwin at the University of California, Santa Barbara in 1974.
  - A Lifetime Narrative Through Artworks, 2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bob Irwin's Lecture at University of California, Santa Barbara, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Printed Material, 1963-1997; 2009-2016; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, OV 5
  Printed material includes exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, magazines, clippings, posters, and a copy of James Turrell's syllabus and course materials for a course taught at the University of California, Santa Barbara.
  - Exhibition Announcements and Posters, 1968-1990; 2010; 2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Oversized material housed in OV 5.
  - Oversized Exhibition Posters, 1968; 1983-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
  - Exhibition Catalogs - Plastics West-Coast, Transparency/Reflection, Separate Realities, 1967-1968; 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Catalogs - Word Works, A Drawing Show, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Catalogs - A View Through, Santa Barbara Drawings, We All Were Here, Global Kiva Tableau, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Catalogs - Richard Aber, Doug Edge, Jud Fine, Adjustments Must Be Made Continually, 1978; 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Catalogs - Il Legno '96, Doug Edge: The Thorn Pieces, or Bramble's Way, 1996-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Catalog - Surf's Up!, Let Me Explain, Plastic Perspective, Permutations: Light and Color, 2011; 2013; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Eclipse no. 2, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Forum vol. 1, no. 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Jim Turrell Syllabus for College of Creative Studies, UCSB, circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Clipping, 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
- Photographic Material, 1962-1987; 2003-2017; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 4, OV 5; 0.438 Gigabytes 138 computer files
  Photographic material includes photographs Edge took on a trip with James Turrell to Monument Valley and Lake Powell; photographs and digital photographs of works of art, and oversized photographs related to his exhibitions.
  - Photographs of Monument Valley and Lake Powell, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, circa 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Digital Photographs of Works of Art, 2003-2017; Archival Resource Key; 0.438 Gigabytes 138 computer files (Box ER02)
  - Oversized Photographs, 1962-1987; circa 2007-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
- Artwork, 1962-1984; 2002; 2007; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 4, OV 5
  Artwork includes sketches, drawings, watercolors, silk screen prints, paintings, and other works of art.
  - Watercolor Paintings, 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Artwork, 1962-1984; 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
- Unprocessed Addition, 1969-2020; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet
  - Unprocessed Papers, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)